What is going on a push peeps? We have
period 5 in 10 minutes for you today.
This one covers from 1844 to 1877.
Before we begin, it is shout out time.
Shout out to Mrs. Lance's class at North
High School. Thank you for watching. I
appreciate your support. All right,
let's get started with US expansion
manifest destiny. Know it. It is
mentioned in the new curriculum. This
was based according to the new
curriculum on racial and cultural
superiority. be familiar with this
painting which depicts Colombia
expanding out west. It is the main focus
of political debates in the 1840s and
the 1850s because as the US expand is
expanding the number one question will
be will that land be free or slave. So
as US is acquiring territory look at
things like the Mexican-American war
which produces the Mexican session which
increases the size of the US by 1/3.
There are enormous debates over slavery.
Things like the Wilmont proviso which
proposes that all slavery be banned in
the Mexican territory. This does not
become a law but it is an idea. So what
is the impacts of expansion? Well, we
have environmental changes and
settlement on Indian lands and this
leads to conflict and treaty violations
with the natives. And there's a picture
of David Wilmod, the author of the
Wilmont proviso. We also have the US
beginning initiatives towards Asia.
especially for economic reasons like
Matthew Perry who goes over to Japan and
cultural reasons as well including
missionaries or the spread of
Christianity. Now we have we're going to
shift our focus to old immigrants during
this time period which tended to live in
ethnic communities and we have those
that are German and Irish that make up
the bulk of old immigrants. The Irish
tend to settle in city cities and the
Germans tend to settle on frontier as
farmers. They came to America pre-ivil
war. That's what separates them from the
new immigrants who will be post civil
war we'll talk about later. They face
nativism which is fear, discrimination,
hatred of foreigners and especially the
Irish because they were Catholic. And
then this nivist movement was
anti-atholic and sought to limit the
power and influence of these immigrants.
Think of the no nothing party which was
established to keep Catholics from
holding office. There were many
opportunities out west during this time
period and it increased due to
legislation promoting economic
development. That's a key point to know
that the federal government is
encouraging westward expansion. Think of
things like the Homestead Act. And
here's a picture of the Homestead Act
gave 160 acres of cheap land to move out
west to families that would settle there
for 5 years. Now, not always was this
land the best. So, what are impacts of
expansion, whether it's migrant or
territorial? Well, we have conflicts
with Hispanics and natives. An example
is the Sand Creek Massacre in which a
Colorado militia attacked the Cheyenne
Indians and killed over a hundred. Most
of them were women and children. And we
also have Little Bigghorn, which is also
known as Kuster's last stand, in which
the natives attacked and killed Kuster
and his men. This was one of the few
successes in conflicts for the Native
Americans. All right, we're going to
jump on over to Northern and Southern
differences. North during this time had
free labor, manufacturing, and the South
was dependent on agriculture and
slavery. They had a very slow population
growth because people are not moving to
the South and competing with slavery. As
a result, the North had more power in
the House, which is why the Wilmont
Proviso passes the House but not the
Senate. Abolitionists begin to emerge
during this time. They are a minority or
small number in the North, but they had
a visible campaign. They use things like
fierce arguments. Dudes like William
Lloyd Garrison here wrote his weekly
newspaper, The Liberator. They also
helped slaves escape, think of the
Underground Railroad, and they use
violence, think of people like John
Brown as well. So how did the south
defend slavery in the face of the
abolitionist movement? Well, people like
John C. Calhoun argued that slavery was
a positive good and they also used
nullification to believe that states
could declare federal laws
unconstitutional. That states had lots
of rights to defend this institution.
And furthermore, they used racial
stereotypes, things like minstal shows
which stereotyped and mocked
African-Americans.
All right, compromises and the election
of 1860. Definitely know this page. So
what were various attempts, failed
attempts at solving the issue of
slavery? Well, you have the compromise
of 1850. This is a result of the land
gain from the Mexican session. We got my
boy Henry Clay here. It instituted
popular sovereignty in the Mexican
session and a strict fugitive slave law
which will greatly upset the North and
lead many to to join the abolitionist
movement. The Kansas Nebraska Act led to
bleeding Kansas and this overturned the
Missouri Compromise and instituted
popular sovereignty in Kansas and
Nebraska. The Dread Scott decision was
an 1857 Supreme Court case which ruled
that Congress could not legislate
slavery in the territories. I do have
detailed videos on all three of these.
Check them out in the description below.
So, the second party system, the Wigs
and the Democrats, that ends due to
issues over slavery and anti-immigrant
nivism nivism. Again, think of the no
nothing party. And we see the mergence
of sectional parties, especially
Republicans in the North and Midwest.
specifically mentioned. Please know that
the Republicans start as a sectional
party. Now, in the election of 1860,
that's when a blank wins. He was elected
on a free soil platform, which meant
that the slavery would not expand. So,
slavery was fine where it is. It just
could not expand beyond that. And this
is the immediate cause of secession.
South Carolina secedes about a month
later and that ultimately leads to the
Civil War.
Okay, let's talk about the Civil War.
Now, the Union victory. The North and
the South both mobilized their economies
and societies for the war effort, even
in the face of serious opposition. Both
instituted conscription or a draft.
Lincoln suspended habius corpus in
Maryland to those that criticized the
war effort and he shut down many
newspapers. The Emancipation
Proclamation, know this, it's in the new
curriculum. It changed the purpose of
the war. It was no longer just to
preserve the Union. And this helped keep
Europe out of the war. And it also led
to African-Americans being able to fight
in the Union Army. And this could be
compared with the Gettysburg address
which hints at a new birth of freedom.
So why did the Union succeed? Well, they
had improved military leadership, people
like Grant and Sherman. They had
effective strategies like the Anaconda
Plan here which was a blockade. And they
had key victories like Antidum which led
to the Emancipation Proclamation and
Gettysburg. They also had greater
resources, more factories, more
railroads, more population. And the
South was destroyed as a result of the
war. or think of Sherman's march to the
sea in which much of the South's
infrastructure and environment was
destroyed. All right, we're going to
jump to reconstruction. 13th Amendment
abolished slavery. This was drastic
social and economic change. However, the
South tried to get around this by
instituting things like sharecropping,
which had conditions very similar to
slavery. Radical Republicans were a
group that emerged during this time and
they sought to change the balance of
power between Congress and the
president. Think of something like the
impeachment of Andrew Johnson. Former
slaves and African-Americans gained
political opportunities.
Herm rebels was the first
African-American elected to Congress. So
you see quite a few number of
African-Americans men who are elected to
Congress. And the word waning and
there's herm rebels. The word waning
means to reduce. And by the 1870s, the
North's resolve for reconstruction was
waning or the North's desire to pursue
reconstruction policies decreased.
Please be familiar with that. Now, the
compromise of 1877 ended reconstruction
and the military was withdrawn from the
south and Rutherford behazes becomes
president. I have a video on that. Check
it out on the description if you want
more. The 14th amendment provided
citizenship and equal protection of the
laws. It's a very key part of this
amendment. I do have a video on 13th,
14th, and 15th amendments. The 15th
amendment granted suffrage for men. So,
you see all men being able to vote here,
and this was aimed specifically at
African-Americans. However,
African-American rights were still
limited during this time through the
following. You have segregation, Jim
Crow laws, which allowed for separate
facilities. You have violence. Groups
like the KKK and the White League
emerge, which terrorized
African-Americans. The Supreme Court
also helped limit African-American
rights through things like PI versus
Ferguson, which established the separate
but equal doctrine and also the civil
rights cases which stated that the
government cannot
stop private and private businesses or
individuals from discrimination and
local political tactics including pole
taxes, literacy tests, and grandfather
clauses which were created to limit the
number of African-Americans
who could vote. So, what were the
impacts of these amendments on women's
rights? Please know that this is a key
part of the new curriculum. It split the
group. Some of them only advocated the
15th amendment if it would include
women, people like Elizabeth Katy Stan
and Susan B. Anthony, and others argued
that the amendment should be passed
because African-Americans had suffered
long enough. Now, these amendments were
stalled for many decades. But eventually
in the 1950s and 1960s, this is a great
connection across time, which the new AP
curriculum loves to do. These amendments
will be used to help out the civil
rights movement. We'll see that when
Brown versus Board overturns Py versus
Ferguson. All right, we'll do a quick
recap. Manifest Destiny and its impacts,
note, especially as it relates to
slavery. Mexicanamean War and debates
over slavery. Think of the Wilma
proviso. Immigrants and nativism. How
did they face discrimination?
Abolitionist tactics. be familiar with
three of them. That's like a great short
answer question. Compromise of 1850. The
Kansas Nebraska Act to Dread Scott. Know
all of them and how they ultimately all
failed. The election of 1860 and
Lincoln's platform as a free soiler.
What did that lead to? The Emancipation
Proclamation and how it changed the war.
Everything about the 13th, 14th, and
15th amendments and the end of
reconstruction and the word waning.
Don't forget waning. All right. Short
answer practice for you. Answer all
three parts. Briefly explain one
political or social impact brought about
by one of the reconstruction amendments.
Briefly explain one way southern society
sought to limit the power of the
amendment chosen in part A. And C,
briefly explain why southern societies
were or were not successful in limiting
the amendments using specific historical
evidence. All right, guys. Thank you
very much for watching. I look forward
to seeing you right back here for period
6 in 10 minutes. We're going to get into
this guy, Booker T. Washington. If you
have any questions or comments, feel
free to leave them in the section below.
Please check out my other videos,
including my massive period 1 through 5
review video in the description and 6
through 9 as well. They are great
resources for both midterms and finals.
And best of luck this year. I do
appreciate your support. Look forward to
seeing you right back here for period 6.
Thank you very much and have a good